<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tjerk.art/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tjerk.art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-30T18:54:35+02:00</updated><id>https://tjerk.art/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tjerk Dijkstra, designs for humans</title><subtitle>Tjerk Dijkstra is a programmer, designer and lecturer based in the north of the Netherlands. He likes to make durable and accessible applications and websites.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What’s my name</title><link href="https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s my name" /><published>2022-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_1.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-next-web--javascript-challenge-1--difficulty-510">The Next Web \ Javascript challenge #1 \ Difficulty: (5/10)</h1>

<p>Make the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Show all numbers in a HTML page that count from 0 until 100</li>
  <li>If the number in the loop is divisible by 3 show the word: “Next”</li>
  <li>If the number in the loop is divisible by 5 show the word: “Web”</li>
  <li>If the number in the loop is divisible by 3 and by 5 show the word: The Next Web</li>
</ol>

<p>For example.</p>

<p><strong>15</strong> is a number which is divisible by 5 and 3</p>

<p><strong>3</strong> is a number which is divisible by 3</p>

<hr />

<details>
  <summary>Hint 1</summary>

	With Javascript you can select an HTML element, like a DIV and append stuff to it.

	https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Document/getElementById

	https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Node/textContent

</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 2 </summary>
		You can loop with FOR statements.
		https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/for
</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 3</summary>
	You can check if a division has a remainder, so you could see if something is divisable or not.

	https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Operators/Remainder
</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 4</summary>
	Google how to make Fizz Buzz challenge.
</details>]]></content><author><name>Tjerk</name></author><category term="assignments" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Next Web \ Javascript challenge #1 \ Difficulty: (5/10)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fun with filters</title><link href="https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fun with filters" /><published>2022-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tjerk.art/assignments/2022/04/29/assignment_2.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-next-web--javascript-3--difficulty-810">The Next Web \ Javascript #3 \ Difficulty: (8/10)</h1>

<ol>
  <li>Create 4 div’s with a title of your favourite: book, movie, game and song</li>
  <li>Add one of these data attributes: book, movie, game, song to each one of these divs</li>
  <li>Create 4 buttons accordingly: book, movie, game, song</li>
  <li>When you press one of these buttons, only the DIVS containing the corresponding data attribute should be visible.</li>
</ol>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 1</summary>

  A data attribute can be anything.

 https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Howto/Use_data_attributes

</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 2</summary>

  You can hide a div with the css rule display:none.

  https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Element/classList

</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 3</summary>

  You can loop through all elements with a specific classname.

</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 4</summary>

  You can loop through all elements with a specific class.
  You can check the data attribute when you have a specific element.

</details>

<details>
  <summary>Hint 5 [pseudo code]</summary>

  const items = document.querySelectorAll(".item");
  for (var i = 0; i &lt; items; i++) {
    console.log('item: ', items[i]);
    // check data attribute
    // is this diffrent then the button i clicked?
    // hide...
  }

</details>]]></content><author><name>Tjerk</name></author><category term="assignments" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Next Web \ Javascript #3 \ Difficulty: (8/10)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bye Strava</title><link href="https://tjerk.art/blog/2022/04/02/bye-strava.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bye Strava" /><published>2022-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://tjerk.art/blog/2022/04/02/bye-strava</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tjerk.art/blog/2022/04/02/bye-strava.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-unrecorded-run">The Unrecorded Run</h2>

<p>It’s that time again, I mentally prepare for a run. For me personally, there is always some resistance to starting a run. A run after a while, becomes a ritual: preparation, running, and aftercare.</p>

<p>In the preparation phase the random questions hit me, questions like: “Should I record this run?” That specific question leads to more questions: “Can I go fast?”, “How far am I going to run?”, “How do I feel?” Lately I’ve noticed that posting my runs to Strava kinda stresses me out. Because when my run shows up in that feed, the datapoints that get shared with others are kind of intimidating.</p>

<p>Distance/Time/Pace</p>

<p>Why are these three things important to my followers? They might be important to me, actually I don’t really know if they are important to me at all. I am not an athlete, but still it bugs me if I don’t upload or record my run, it almost feels “lost” if I don’t record my progress.</p>

<p>“At this point, it’s really weird to me that I upload my sports activities to a platform that advertises with pictures of professional athletes wearing fancy sunglasses riding bikes that are just as expensive as my car.”</p>

<h2 id="the-kudo-thing">The Kudo thing</h2>

<p>Small confession: I only look at the feed just after I uploaded my run/ride, this sometimes takes a while, and when I have the app open I browse other people’s runs until its finished.</p>

<p>I hand out kudo’s to almost everyone on my feed. Exercise is hard and getting out there and doing something is always something to be appreciated. When I receive my steady flow of 5 kudo’s per run, it helps.
But I see people recording their afternoon walks, indoor bike training and vacation ski events almost obsessively. Every activity counts.. but towards what exactly?</p>

<h2 id="see-ya">See ya</h2>

<p>And I wish you guys good luck, i’d love to jump on a new platform, one that actually motivates me. But it’s kind of discouraging, there is nothing fun about a new empty platform.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Tjerk</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Unrecorded Run]]></summary></entry></feed>